Peggy V. Beck Collection
Library of Congress American Folklife Center Archive of Folk Culture
Peggy V. Beck collection, 1985-1987
AFC 2005/005
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
manuscripts 25 folders.
sound recordings 35 sound cassettes: analog (60 and 90 min.)
graphic materials 691 photographs: photographic prints, slides, negatives, b&w, col.; various sizes.
graphic materials 6 drawings: pencil.
moving images 3 videocassettes (VHS): sd., col.; 1/2 in.
Beck, Peggy V.
This collection comprises research materials created and compiled by Peggy V. Beck for the exhibition Oremos, Oremos: New Mexican Midwinter Masquerades, at the Millicent Rogers Museum in Taos, New Mexico in 1987, as well as documentation of other New Mexican midwinter rituals. Included are sound recordings of interviews, rehearsals, and performances; field notes, photographs, drawings, and videocassettes; plus exhibition catalogs and exhibit scripts. The focus of the exhibition is midwinter celebrations and plays, including Los Matachines, Los Pastores, and Los Días, and photographs and drawings of abuelos and abuelas.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Beck, Peggy V.
Organizations
Millicent Rogers Museum
Subjects
Folk drama, Hispanic American (Spanish)--New Mexico.; Folk songs, Spanish--New Mexico.; Hispanic Americans--New Mexico--Social life and customs.; Masquerades--New Mexico.; Matachines (Dance)--New Mexico.; Matachines (Music)--New Mexico.; New Year music.; New Year--New Mexico.; Winter festivals--New Mexico.
Titles
Exhibition title: Oremos, oremos: New Mexican midwinter masquerades; Former collection title: Peggy V. Beck collection on New Mexican midwinter masquerades
Form/Genre
Exhibition catalogs.; Field recordings--New Mexico.; Interviews.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videocassettes.
Arrangement
Organized by format into the following series: I. Manuscripts; II. Sound Recordings; III. Graphic Images; IV. Moving Images.
Box 2 contained sound recordings that have been transferred to the Library's National Audio-Visual Conservation Center (NAVCC), in Culpeper, Virginia.
Acquisition
The collection was donated to the American Folklife Center by the collector, Dr. Peggy V. Beck, in April 2005.
Access and Restrictions
Collection is open for research; access to collection materials may be restricted. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Biographical Note
Peggy V. Beck, author, educator, received her PhD in the History of Consciousness in 1974 from the University of California, Santa Cruz, under the direction of Gregory Bateson. She taught humanities at the University of New Mexico and at New Mexico Highlands University from 1979-1983.
Beck attended Sarah Lawrence College where she received a B.A. in 1969. Beck had a keen interest in the phenomena of the fool and clown. Beck received a Wenner-Gren fellowship to study ritual clowns and shamans in the Sierra Mixe, Oaxaca, Mexico in 1974. Beck worked for four years at Diné College on the Navajo Nation where she wrote bi-cultural curriculum materials including the textbook, The Sacred: Ways of Knowledge, Sources of Life. The book was first published in 1977 by the Navajo Community College and was reprinted in 1990 by Northern Arizona Press in 1990. Beck lived in northern New Mexico in 1979 where she began teaching humanities at the University of New Mexico and New Mexico Highlands University. In 1986 she received a Folk Arts Program grant from the National Endowment for the Arts to mount an exhibit on New Mexican midwinter masquerades. Beck has written novels, poetry, and published essays relating to the fool in anthologies and in the journal Parabola.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of Peggy V. Beck’s research materials used to create the exhibition Oremos, Oremos: New Mexican Midwinter Masquerades, at the Millicent Rogers Museum in Taos, New Mexico, in 1987, as well as documentation of other New Mexican midwinter rituals. Included are sound recordings of interviews, some of which are transcribed; recordings of performances and transcriptions for some of these interviews; recordings of performances both in the field and at the museum; field notes, photographs, drawings, and videocassettes.
Beck conducted interviews and documented midwinter masquerades in 1986 and 1987 in eight north central New Mexican locations, from Costilla in the north to Ranchos de Taos in the south. The masquerades centered around the figure of the abuelo (a word that normally means "grandfather" but in this context refers to masked ogres or bogeymen that appeared between December 10 and Christmas). The masked abuelos were said to come down from their mountain caves, attracted by luminaria (square-shaped bonfires made from cross-hatched pitch pine logs). The masqueraders went from house to house, dancing and performing. Children were warned that unless they were good, the whip-cracking abuelos would carry them off. On Christmas Eve, the culmination of the festivities, the abuelos and masked young people roamed the countryside asking for Christmas treats.
Beck documented the midwinter celebrations by interviewing elderly Spanish speakers. She found that the abuelos masquerades had elements similar to indigenous Pueblo midwinter rituals as well as characteristics common to solstice celebrations in West Africa, South American, and Europe (among the Basque people, for example).
In addition to the material related to the abuelos/oremos festivities, Beck also collected information pertaining to Los Manueles or Los Dias, a tradition in which singers and accompanying instrumentalists make rounds within communities, performing spontaneous verses in celebrating of the New Year. Los Manueles (literally, the Emmanuels -- people whose patron saint is Jesus, having names like Manuel or Manuela) are celebrated on their saint’s day, January 1. Since all of the days of the New Year are blessed in this way, the custom is also called Los Dias (the Days). Beck also gathered documentation on the matachines, an Indo-Hispano dance drama, performed in some northern New Mexican communities and pueblos. She also documented the Christmas nativity play, Los Pastores.
A list of names and geographic locations where the materials were collected are in Appendix A.
Container List
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - Finding Aid. March 2006., 12 pages. (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Exhibition Brochures. Beck, Peggy V. New Mexican Midwinter Masquerades: Oremos, Oremos. Taos: Millicent Rogers Museum, Inc. 1987., 24 pages. English. (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Beck, Peggy V. "Abuelos y Abuelas: They're coming to take you away." New Mexican Magazine. December 1987: 32-37., 88 pages. English. (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Oremos Exhibit Wall Text at Millicent Rogers Museum. 1987., 28 pages. English. (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Vocabulary. Undated., 3 pages. Spanish and English. (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Handouts. The Dias. Undated., 4 pages. 3 pages. Spanish and English. (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Agreement Forms. 1986-1987., 18 pages. English. (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Jose Damian Archuleta. Taos, New Mexico. Notes from taped interview, SR01 and SR02. March 30, 1987., 11 pages. Spanish and English. (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Ray Archuleta. Aroyo Seco, New Mexico. Notes in English from taped interview, SR03. March 24, 1987., 11 pages. English. (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Lucia Arellano. Dixon, New Mexico. Notes from taped interview, SR04. March 9, 1987., 2 pages. Spanish and English. (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Narcisco Arellano. Arroyo Seco, New Mexico. Notes from taped interview, SR05. May 1, 1987., 2 pages. Spanish. (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Onofre and Maria Inez Baros. Arroyo Seco, New Mexico. Notes from taped interview, SR06 and SR07. May 1, 1987., 7 pages. Spanish and English. (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Amalia Duran. Arroyo Seco, New Mexico. Notes from taped interview, SR08. March 27, 1987. Spanish and English., 7 pages. (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Art Lucero. Abuelo Notes. Notes with no corresponding taped interview. Undated., 5 pages. Spanish and English. (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Mike and Helen Lucero. Amalia, New Mexico. Notes from taped interview, SR10. May 7, 1987., 8 pages. English. (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Casimera Madrid. El Salto, New Mexico. Notes and transcript from taped interview, SR11 and SR12. April 27, 1987., 10 pages. Spanish and English. (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Rudy Mascareñas. Amalia, New Mexico. Notes and transcript from taped interview, SR13 and SR14. November 13, 1986., 13 pages. Spanish and English. (Box-folder 1/17)
  - Levi Mondragon. Los Cordovas, New Mexico. Notes from taped interview, SR15 and SR16. January 8, 1987., 17 pages. English. (Box-folder 1/18)
  - Bernabe Pacheco. Des Montes, New Mexico. Notes from taped interview, SR17 and SR18. May 27, 1987., 4 pages. Spanish and English. (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Cleo Rivera. Costilla, New Mexico. Notes and transcript from taped interview, SR20. May 6, 1987., 13 pages. English. (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Eufelia Romero. Costilla, New Mexico. Notes from taped interview, SR21. March 20, 1987., 4 pages. Spanish. (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Ernestina Sanchez. Cerro, New Mexico. Notes and transcript from taped interviews, SR22. May 29, 1987., 16 pages. Spanish and English. (Box-folder 1/22)
  - Candelaria and Zacarias Torres. Costilla, New Mexico. Notes from taped interview, SR23 and SR24. November 19, 1986., 16 pages. Spanish and English. (Box-folder 1/23)
  - Pilar Trujillo. Taos (El Valle), New Mexico. Notes from taped interview, SR26. May 14, 1987., 4 pages. Spanish and English. (Box-folder 1/24)
  - Compiled quotes of interviews pertaining to different subjects., 40 pages. Spanish and English. (Box-folder 1/25)
- Series II: Sound Recordings
  - Jose Damian Archuleta. Taos, New Mexico. Tape 1 of 2. March 30, 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR01)
  - Jose Damian Archuleta. Taos, New Mexico. Tape 2 of 2. March 30, 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR02)
  - Ray Archuleta. Arroyo Seco, New Mexico. March 24, 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. English. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR03)
  - Lucia Arellano. Dixon, New Mexico. March 9, 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR04)
  - Narcisco Arellano. Arroyo Seco, New Mexico. May 1, 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR05)
  - Onofre and Maria Inez Baros. Arroyo Seco, New Mexico. November 11, 1986., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish and English. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR06)
  - Onofre and Maria Inez Baros. Des Montes, New Mexico. November 21, 1986., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish and English. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR07)
  - Amalia Duran. Arroyo Seco, New Mexico. March 27, 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR08)
  - Demetrio Duran. Pentasco, New Mexico. May 15, 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR09)
  - Mike and Helen Lucero. Amalia, New Mexico. May 7, 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. English. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR10)
  - Casimera Madrid. El Salto, New Mexico. Tape 1 of 2. April 27, 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR11)
  - Casimera Madrid. El Salto, New Mexico. Tape 2 of 2. April 27, 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR12)
  - Rudy Mascareñas. Amalia, New Mexico. November 13, 1986., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish and English. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR13)
  - Rudy Mascareñas. Amalia, New Mexico. May 4, 1986., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish and English. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR14)
  - Levi Mondragon. Los Cordovas, New Mexico. Tape 1 of 2. January 8, 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish and English. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR15)
  - Levi Mondragon. Los Cordovas, New Mexico. Tape 2 of 2. January 8, 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish and English. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR16)
  - Bernabe Pacheco. Des Montes, New Mexico. Tape 1 of 2. May 27, 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR17)
  - Bernabe Pacheco. Des Montes, New Mexico. Tape 2 of 2. May 27, 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR18)
  - Max and Eutilia Padilla. San Cristobal, New Mexico. March 7, 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR19)
  - Cleo Rivera. Costilla, New Mexico. May 6, 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. English. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR20)
  - Eufelia Romero. Costilla, New Mexico. March 20, 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR21)
  - Ernestina Sanchez. Cerro, New Mexico. May 29, 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish and English. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR22)
  - Candelaria and Zacarias Torres. Costilla, New Mexico. Tape 1 of 2. November 19, 1986. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR23)
  - Candelaria and Zacarias Torres. Costilla, New Mexico. Tape 2 of 2. November 19, 1986., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR24)
  - Pablita Trujillo. San Cristobal, New Mexico. April 23, 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish and English. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR25)
  - Pilar Trujillo. Taos (El Valle), New Mexico. May 14, 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR26)
  - Pete Valdez (with Onofre Baros). December 11, 1986., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR27)
  - Side A: El Año Viejo y El Año Nuevo. Stateline Bar. Costilla, New Mexico. December 31, 1985. Side B: Versos de Año. Costilla, New Mexico. January 1, 1986., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish and English. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR28)
  - Matachines Rehearsal. Cuna Music for Los Dias. Costilla, New Mexico. January 1, 1986., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR29)
  - Side A: Matachines Rehearsal. Arroyo Hondo, New Mexico. 1985. Side B: Los Dias. Abuelos. Sung by Rey Torres. Arroyo Seco, New Mexico. Undated., 1 90-minute audiocassette. Spanish. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR30)
  - Side A: Los Dias. Costilla, New Mexico. January 1, 1986. Side B: Torres recorded by Everts. June 18, 1985., 1 90-minute audiocassette. Spanish. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR31)
  - Los Dias. Amalia, New Mexico. January 1, 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR32)
  - Los Dias in the home of Alfonso Gonzales. Año Nuevo. Amalia, New Mexico. January 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR33)
  - Abuelos. Levi Mondragon. December 16, 1987., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR34)
  - Los Manueles. Undated., 1 60-minute audiocassette. Spanish. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: SR35)
- Series III: Graphic Materials
  - Subseries A: Photographs
    - New Mexico: Midwinter Rituals. New Year’s play, Matachines rehearsal, Los Pastores, and Abuelos Noche Buena. 1985., 146 color slides. (Box-folder 3/26)
    - Arroyo Seco Abuelos. Arroyo Seco, New Mexico. Out of season. June 9, 1985., 33 color photographs. (Box-folder 3/27)
    - Selected Matachines Dance. (Abuelos). Arroyo Seco, New Mexico. June 9, 1985., 17 color slides. (Box-folder 3/28)
    - Amalia Abuelos. Amalia, New Mexico. Undated., 33 color photographs. (Box-folder 3/29)
    - Amalia Abuelos. Rudy Mascareñas (Making chicote). Amalia, New Mexico. Undated., 4 color photographs.; 23 black-and-white photographs.; 23 black-and-white negative frames. (Box-folder 3/30)
    - Amalia Abuelos. Los Cordovas Abuelos. Amalia Dias. Los Cordovas Comanches. Undated., 10 color contact sheets.; 360 color negatives. (Box-folder 3/31)
    - Death of Old Year. Birth of New Year. Dando Los Dias from house to house. Amalia, New Mexico. 1986-1987., 14 color slides.; 35 color photographs. (Box-folder 3/32)
    - Costilla New Years Day and Dias. Torres Family. Costilla, New Mexico. 1985-1986., 21 color photographs. (Box-folder 3/33)
    - Costilla New Year. Costilla, New Mexico. Undated., 22 color slides. (Box-folder 3/34)
    - Los Cordovas Comanches. New Years. (Levi Mondragon). Undated., 53 color photographs. (Box-folder 3/35)
    - Slides of Exhibit Wall Text at Millicent Rogers Museum. 1987., 43 color slides. (Box-folder 3/36)
    - Notes and slides removed from slide carousel. Circa 1986., 16 black-and-white slides.; 33 color slides.; 3 pages. (Box-folder 3/37)
    - Color Slides [Unlabeled]. Undated., 17 color slides. (Box-folder 3/38)
    - Alamosa Folklife Festival. Lala Torres and Alice Valdez. Undated., 25 color photographs. (Box-folder 3/39)
      Photographs are not Abuelo related except that Lala Torres was interviewed for the Oremos exhibit and made the Abuela for the exhibit.
  - Subseries B: Drawings, Original drawings of abuelos by Levi Mondragon from Los Cordovas, New Mexico. (Box 4)
    - Abuelo. Undated., 1 drawing in pencil. 17 in. x 11 in. (ITEM ID AFC 2005/005: GR01)
    - Abuelo holding a chicote (whip). Undated., 1 drawing in pencil. 16.5 in. x 8.5 in. (ITEM ID AFC 2005/005: GR02)
    - Abuelo wearing a hat. Undated., 1 drawing in pencil. 17 in. x 11 in. (ITEM ID AFC 2005/005: GR03)
    - Abuelo wearing a hat and a shirt with "Golden Grain" written on it. Undated., 1 drawing in pencil. 17 in. x 11 in. (ITEM ID AFC 2005/005: GR04)
    - Abuelo holding a flour sack with "Raton Flour Mill, 1930" written on it. Undated., 1 drawing in pencil. 14.5 in. x 14.5 in. (ITEM ID AFC 2005/005: GR05)
    - Abuelo holding a flour sack with "Raton Flour Mill, 1930" written on it. Undated., 17.5 in. x 12 in. (ITEM ID AFC 2005/005: GR06)
      Facsimile of GR05
- Series IV: Moving Images
  - Oremos, Oremos and Raw Footage. Undated., 1 VHS color videocassette with sound. Approximately 1 hour. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: MV01)
  - Matachines Dances. San Juan. Copy. Undated., 1 VHS color videocassette with sound. Approximately 30 minutes. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: MV02)
  - Millicent Rogers New Years Play. El Año Viejo y El Año Nuevo. December 30, 1987., 1 VHS color videocassette with sound. Approximately 1 hour. (TAPE ID AFC 2005/005: MV03)
APPENDIX A: Names and Locations Where Materials Were Collected
Personal names
Jose Damian Archuleta
Ray Archuleta
Lucia Arellano
Narcisco Arellano
Onofre Baros
Maria Inez Baros
Amalia Duran
Demetrio Duran
Alfonso Gonzales
Art Lucero
Mike Lucero
Helen Lucero
Casimera Madrid
Rudy Mascareñas
Levi Mondragon
Bernabe Pacheco
Max Padilla
Eutilia Padilla
Cleo Rivera
Eufelia Romero
Ernestina Sanchez
Candelaria Torres
Rey Torres
Zacarias Torres
Pablita Trujillo
Pilar Trujillo
Pete Valdez
Geographic names
Amalia (N.M.)
Arroyo Seco (N.M.)
Cerro (N.M.)
Costilla (N.M.)
Des Montes (N.M.)
Dixon (N.M.)
El Salto (N.M.)
Los Cordovas (N.M.)
Peñasco (N.M.)
San Cristobal (N.M.)
Taos (N.M.)
Taos Pueblo (N.M.)